A Guide to the Papers of Dorothy M. Jones, 1954-1983
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Dorothy M. Jones 1954-1983
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
18-4A1
1.5 Linear feet, 4 document cases
Jones, Dorothy M.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dorothy M. Jones, October 28, 1976
Biographical Information
Ms. Jones was a professor at Old Dominion University from 1954-1976. She retired after 20 years of teaching and passed away in 1992. Ms. Jones was one of four children of a schoolteacher. Ms. Jones attended Randolph Macon Women's College from 1928 until 1932, when she graduated with her Bachelor's degree in Abnormal Psychology. After graduating from Randolph Macon, Dorothy Jones was offered two fellowships. She decided to accept the fellowship offered by New York University. In 1933, she graduated with a Masters degree in Marketing from New York University.
After graduation, Jones began her business career by being retained at Stern Brothers as an Assistant Buyer in the Fashion Department. She later transferred to Lord and Taylor and served in a similar position. Jones would eventually end up working for Consolidated Millinery Department and through that company would be transferred to 3 different states during her 14-year employment with the company.
It was when Jones suffered a foot injury that required surgery that she decided to pursue a teaching career. So Jones joined Old Dominion University (then the Norfolk Division of the College of William and Mary) as the Head of the Merchandising Department in 1954. Jones served as the Assistant Professor of Distributive Education during her career in the Merchandising Department as well. When she left that Distributive Education, Ms. Branigan and Joe Bigs followed her to fill that position. Jones served in the capacity of Head of Merchandising for five years until 1959 when she left that position to become the Associate Professor of Business Management in the School of Business, until her retirement in 1976. Jones retired with Emeritus status and she was an integral figure in promoting the conception, establishment, and organization of the ODU Emeriti program.
During her career at Old Dominion University, Jones eventually sought funds from local businesses to establish the founding of a Chair of Merchandising within the Business Department. She was unable to obtain this goal before her retirement, a fact that disappointed her. There are two scholarships at Old Dominion University that are connected to Dorothy Jones. The first is one that she established in honor of her parents, which is the Bagwell-Jones scholarship. The second scholarship shows the popularity of Jones with her students and the impact that she had on their lives. A former student of Jones' established it anonymously in her honor.
Time Line
Date Event
1928-1932 Randolph Macon Women's College (B.A., Abnormal Psychology)
1933 New York University (M.A., Marketing)
1933-1954 Business career (Stern Bros., Lord and Taylor, Consolidated Millinery Department)
1954 Norfolk College of William and Mary (Head of Merchandising Department)
1954-1959 Head of Merchandising Department (Distributive Education)
1959-1962 Summer school at Chapel Hill (working towards Doctorate)
1960-1976 Associate Professor of Business Management in School of Business
1976 Retires from Old Dominion University
1992 Died
Scope and Content
This collection deals primarily with Dr. Jones career as a professor at the Norfolk Division of the College of William and Mary. The papers document her studies conducted through classes for the benefit of local businessmen, business correspondence, papers and published materials. There is very little personal information or papers included in this collection. Materials in the archives consist of directories; reports; studies; pamphlets; papers; correspondence; newspaper clippings; photos; speeches, and various other materials in addition to those listed here.
Arrangement
The collection is broken down chronologically during the time that Dorothy Jones spent in her career at the Norfolk Division of the College of William and Mary. The collection is divided into four series.
Contents List
- Head of Merchandising 1954-1959
  This series contains pictures, papers and material relating to Dorothy M. Jones during her time as the Head of the Merchandising Department.
  Chronologically
  - Articles relating to Ms. Jones during her tenure as Dept. Head (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Paperwork filed with Distributive Education (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Pennywise Shopping Survey (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Graduate Paper by Ms. Jones submitted at Chapel Hill, Newspaper articles relating to Ms. Jones at Chapel Hill (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence and subsequent publications with The National Research Bureau (Box-folder 1:5)
- Associate Professor of Business Management (1960-1976-Retirement). 1960-1976
  This series contains pictures, papers and material relating to Dorothy M. Jones during her tenure with the Department of Business Management. Of particular interest would be the number of Shopping surveys Ms. Jones completed during this time.
  - Shopping Survey (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Graduate Paper by Ms. Jones submitted at Chapel Hill (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Essays and Publications (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Research, and papers on the Williamsburg Pottery (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Newspaper articles on the Williamsburg Pottery (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Newspaper articles relating to Ms. Jones as Assoc. Prof. of Business Management (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Materials relating to class (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Materials relating to the ODU Campus (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Guidelines for Professors Handbook (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Shopping Survey (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Naval Supply Center Speech (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Material relating to GEX (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Material relating to ODC Student Wives' Club (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Essays and Publications (Box-folder 2:10)
- Retirement 1976-1983
  This series contains papers that were in the collection that are dated after her retirement. The papers related mainly to Emeriti matters.
  Chronological
  - Material relating to Emeriti Matters (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Blue Cross/Blue Shield Emeriti Paperwork (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Material relating to the ODU Library (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Miscellaneous paperwork (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Woolworth Book (Box-folder 2:15)
  - North Carolina Court of Appeals Book (Box-folder 2:16)
- Albums/Scrapbooks 1954-1958
  This series is interesting and valuable as it contains the scrapbooks and albums that Ms. Jones constructed herself. The original were preserved through copies and the original material was removed in the interests of preservation. The documents in this series range from a number of photographs to programs for events and personal letters and correspondence
  chronological
  - Copy of the Original Scrapbook 1955 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook 1955 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Copy of the Original Scrapbook - Volume One 1954-1957 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook - Volume One 1954-1957 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Copy of the Original Scrapbook- Volume Two 1954-1957 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook- Volume Two 1954-1957 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Copy of the Original Scrapbook - Book One 1956-1957 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook - Book One 1956-1957 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Copy of the Original Scrapbook - Book Two 1957 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook- Book Two 1957 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Copy of the Original Scrapbook- Book Three 1957 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook- Book Three 1957 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Copy of Original Scrapbook- 1957-1958 1957-1958 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Original Material from Scrapbook 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4:17)